Or, we decide that we're going to prevent dementia, and it will never happen to us because we're going to do everything right and it won't come and get us. I'm looking for a third way: I'm preparing to get Alzheimer's disease. Prevention is good, and I'm doing the things that you can do to prevent Alzheimer's. I'm eating right, I'm exercising every day, I'm keeping my mind active, that's what the research says you should do. But the research also shows that there's nothing that will 100 percent protect you. If the monster wants you, the monster's gonna get you. That's what happened with my dad. My dad was a bilingual college professor. His hobbies were chess, bridge and writing op-eds. (Laughter) He got dementia anyway. If the monster wants you, the monster's gonna get you. Especially if you're me, 'cause Alzheimer's tends to run in families. So I'm preparing to get Alzheimer's disease. Based on what I've learned from taking care of my father, and researching what it's like to live with dementia, I'm focusing on three things in my preparation: I'm changing what I do for fun, I'm working to build my physical strength, and -- this is the hard one -- I'm trying to become a better person. Let's start with the hobbies. When you get dementia, it gets harder and harder to enjoy yourself. You can't sit and have long talks with your old friends, because you don't know who they are. It's confusing to watch television, and often very frightening. And reading is just about impossible. When you care for someone with dementia, and you get training, they train you to engage them in activities that are familiar, hands-on, open-ended. With my dad, that turned out to be letting him fill out forms. He was a college professor at a state school; he knows what paperwork looks like. He'll sign his name on every line, he'll check all the boxes, he'll put numbers in where he thinks there should be numbers. But it got me thinking, what would my caregivers do with me? I'm my father's daughter. I read, I write, I think about global health a lot. Would they give me academic journals so I could scribble in the margins? Would they give me charts and graphs that I could color? So I've been trying to learn to do things that are hands-on. I've always liked to draw, so I'm doing it more even though I'm really very bad at it. I am learning some basic origami. I can make a really great box. (Laughter) And I'm teaching myself to knit, which so far I can knit a blob. But, you know, it doesn't matter if I'm actually good at it. What matters is that my hands know how to do it. Because the more things that are familiar, the more things my hands know how to do, the more things that I can be happy and busy doing when my brain's not running the show anymore. They say that people who are engaged in activities are happier, easier for their caregivers to look after, and it may even slow the progress of the disease. That all seems like win to me. I want to be as happy as I can for as long as I can. A lot of people don't know that Alzheimer's actually has physical symptoms, as well as cognitive symptoms. You lose your sense of balance, you get muscle tremors, and that tends to lead people to being less and less mobile. They get scared to walk around. They get scared to move. So I'm doing activities that will build my sense of balance. I'm doing yoga and tai chi to improve my balance, so that when I start to lose it, I'll still be able to be mobile. I'm doing weight-bearing exercise, so that I have the muscle strength so that when I start to wither, I have more time that I can still move around. Finally, the third thing. I'm trying to become a better person. My dad was kind and loving before he had Alzheimer's, and he's kind and loving now. I've seen him lose his intellect, his sense of humor, his language skills, but I've also seen this: He loves me, he loves my sons, he loves my brother and my mom and his caregivers. And that love makes us want to be around him, even now. even when it's so hard. When you take away everything that he ever learned in this world, his naked heart still shines. I was never as kind as my dad, and I was never as loving. And what I need now is to learn to be like that. I need a heart so pure that if it's stripped bare by dementia, it will survive. I don't want to get Alzheimer's disease. What I want is a cure in the next 20 years, soon enough to protect me. But if it comes for me, I'm going to be ready. Thank you. (Applause)
O, nos decidimos a prevenir la demencia, y jamás nos pasará porque haremos todo correctamente y nunca vendrá por nosotros. Yo intento buscar una tercera vía: me estoy preparando para tener Alzheimer. Prevenir es bueno, y me he propuesto hacer todo lo que se puede hacer para evitar el Alzheimer. Como de manera saludable, hago ejercicio cada día, mantengo mi mente activa, eso es lo que las investigaciones dicen que deberíamos hacer. Pero esas investigaciones también aseguran que no existe nada que pueda protegernos al 100%. Si el monstruo va a por ti, te alcanzará. Eso es lo que ocurrió con mi padre. Mi padre era profesor bilingüe de Instituto. Sus aficiones eran el ajedrez, el bridge y escribir artículos de opinión. (Risas) Y aun así desarrolló demencia. Si el monstruo va a por ti, te alcanzará. Sobre todo si eres yo, pues el Alzheimer tiende a ser una enfermedad hereditaria. Así que me estoy preparando para tener Alzheimer. En base a lo que he aprendido cuidando a mi padre, e investigando acerca de cómo es vivir con demencia, me estoy centrando en tres puntos para mi preparación: Estoy cambiando las actividades que realizo por diversión, trabajando para mejorar mi fuerza física, y, esta es la parte complicada: Estoy intentando convertirme en mejor persona. Empecemos por los hobbies. Cuando tienes demencia, cada vez es más y más difícil divertirte. No puedes sentarte y tener conversaciones con tus viejos amigos, porque no los reconoces. Ver la televisión es confuso, y a menudo intimida y asusta. Y leer se hace casi imposible. Cuando cuidas a alguien con demencia, y te entrenan para ello, te enseñan a hacerles participar en actividades familiares para ellos, prácticas e indefinidas. En el caso de mi padre, el resultado fue dejarle rellenar informes. Era profesor en una universidad pública; sabe qué aspecto tiene el papeleo burocrático. Él firma con su nombre en cada renglón, marca todas las casillas, escribe números donde cree que deberían escribirse. Pero eso me hace pensar: ¿qué harían mis cuidadores conmigo? Soy como mi padre. Leo, escribo, pienso mucho acerca de la salud global. ¿Me darían revistas académicas para que pudiese garabatear en los márgenes? ¿Me darían tablas y gráficos que pudiese colorear? Por eso he estado intentando aprender a hacer cosas manuales y prácticas. Siempre me ha gustado dibujar, así que lo hago más a menudo, aunque no sea muy buena. Estoy aprendiendo a hacer origamis sencillos. Ya sé hacer una caja increíble. (Risas) Y estoy aprendiendo a tejer, de momento sé tejer una bola. Pero, ¿saben? realmente no importa si soy buena. Lo que importa es que mis manos saben cómo hacerlo. Porque cuantas más cosas me sean familiares, más recordarán mis manos, más cosas podrán mantenerme ocupada y feliz haciéndolas cuando mi cerebro ya no dirija el timón. Dicen que las personas que realizan muchas actividades son más felices, que es más fácil cuidarlas y que esto incluso puede ralentizar el avance de la enfermedad. Para mí, eso es ganar la partida. Quiero ser todo lo feliz que pueda durante todo el tiempo que me sea posible. Mucha gente desconoce el hecho de que el Alzheimer implica tanto síntomas físicos, como síntomas cognitivos. Pierdes el sentido del equilibrio, tus músculos tienen espasmos, y eso suele dejar a la gente cada vez menos y menos móvil. Les asusta caminar. Les asusta incluso moverse. Así que estoy realizando actividades que entrenen mi sentido del equilibrio. Hago yoga y tai chi para mejorar mi equilibrio, para que cuando empiece a perderlo, aún sea capaz de moverme. Hago ejercicio con pesas, de modo que tenga la fuerza física para que, cuando empiece a atrofiarme, disponga de más tiempo de movilidad. Por último, el tercer paso, estoy intentando mejorar como persona. Mi padre era amable y cariñoso antes de tener Alzheimer, y es amable y cariñoso ahora también. He visto cómo perdía su inteligencia, su sentido del humor, sus habilidades lingüísticas, pero también he visto esto: me quiere, adora a mis hijos, quiere a mi hermano, a mi madre y a sus cuidadores. Y ese amor hace que queramos estar cerca de él, incluso ahora, a pesar de lo difícil que resulta. Cuando lo despojas de todo lo que aprendió durante su vida, su desnudo corazón aún brilla. Nunca he sido tan amable como mi padre, y tampoco tan cariñosa. Y lo que necesito ahora es aprender a ser así. Necesito un corazón tan puro que, aun desprovisto de todo por la demencia, pueda sobrevivir. No quiero tener Alzheimer. Lo que quiero es una cura en los próximos 20 años, suficientemente pronto para que me proteja. Pero si la enfermedad viene por mí, estaré preparada. Gracias. (Aplausos)